Finding Aid for Marguerite Novy Lambert papers, 1910-1920s and 1974-1982
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Marguerite Novy Lambert papers
1910-1920s
1974-1982
Lambert, Marguerite Novy.
851705 Aa 2; AA; UAm
Student at the University of Michigan, later Ann Arbor, Michigan local historian. Listings of death and marriage notices from selective counties taken from Michigan newspapers at the Bentley Historical Library; also other papers, scrapbook 1910-1913, of activities while a student at the University of Michigan; and photographs.
0.4 linear feet
14 volumes
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Marguerite Novy Lambert (donor no. 4339 ).
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
Marguerite Felice Novy (married Lambert) was the daughter of Frederick G. Novy, bacteriologist and head of the University of Michigan Medical School. Marguerite was nicknamed "Peggy" in childhood and lived with her family at 721 South Forest in Ann Arbor. She received the B.A. from the College of Literature Science and Art in 1919 and did some graduate work in 1918-1919. She worked briefly for the Detroit Department of Health. In the 1920's she lived with Irene Ellis Murphy in Detroit. Marguerit Lambert was a dedicated and professional genealogist.
The collection is comprised of two series: Personal and Genealogical and other Research Materials.
The photographic materials deal mainly with the youth of Mrs. Lambert and her brother Frederick G. Novy, Jr. in Ann Arbor, Michigan. Included are two albums relating to Mrs. Lambert's childhood and youth at Ann Arbor, the University of Michigan, and at camp in New Hampshire. There is also a scrapbook of clippings and other memorabilia from the period when she was a student at the University of Michigan, 1910-1913.
The genealogical material consist of fourteen volumes, arranged alphabetically, and containing death and marriage notices from Michigan newspapers up to approximately 1865.
Subjects:
Adrian (Mich.)--History.; Allegan County (Mich.); Ann Arbor (Mich.)--History.; Barry County (Mich.); Bay County (Mich.); Berrien County (Mich.); Branch County (Mich.); Calhoun County (Mich.); Detroit gazette.; Detroit (Mich.)--History.; Eaton County (Mich.); Genesee County (Mich.); Grand Traverse County (Mich.); Hillsdale County (Mich.); Houghton County (Mich.); Ingham County (Mich.); Jackson County (Mich.); Kalamazoo County (Mich.); Kent County (Mich.); Lenawee County (Mich.); Livingston County (Mich.); Montcalm County (Mich.); Oakland County (Mich.); Ontonagon County (Mich.); Ottawa County (Mich.); Registers of births, etc.--Michigan.; Saginaw County (Mich.); Saint Joseph County (Mich.); University of Michigan--History.History.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1901-1910.StudentsSocial life and customs1901-1910.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1911-1920.StudentsSocial life and customs1911-1920.; Washtenaw County (Mich.); Wayne County (Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Alpha Epsilon Iota. Alpha Chapter (University of Michigan); Ann Arbor High School (Mich.). Class of 1915.; Ann Arbor High School (Mich.)--Football.Football.; Camps.; Collegiate Sorosis (University of Michigan); Costumes.; Children playing.; Dwellings.; Interiors.; Living rooms--1911-1920.; Novy, Frederick George, 1864-1957.; Novey family.; Photography.; Recreation.; University of Michigan--Campus.Campus.; University of Michigan--Football.Football.; University of Michigan. School of Information and Library Studies.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1911-1920.StudentsSocial life and customs1911-1920.
Genre Terms:
Albums.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Personal
  - Photographs
    - Collegiate Sorosis, 1915-1919 (Box 1)
      (see also UAm)
    - Miscellaneous, 1915-1920s (Box 1)
  - Albums
    - Album No. 1 (childhood), circa 1910-1916 (Box 1)
      (Includes Novy home at 721 South Forest. Scenes from Whitmore Lake, Cavanaugh Lake, Winans Lake, and Frankfort. Campfire girls and camp scenes. Michigan Union Opera. Campus scenes. Neighborhood children shown are Margaret Cooley, daughter of Charles Horton Cooley, Gay Wilgus, daughter of Horace Wilgus, Evelyn Van Tyne, daughter of Claude Van Tyne, Julia Peterson, daughter of Reuben Peterson, Hester Reid, Margaret Henderson and the children of neighbor Victor Hugo Lane.)
    - Album No. 2, 1913-1918 (Box 1)
      (The first two-thirds of the volume devoted to activities at Camp Winnecomack near Munsonville, New Hampshire, in 1913. Five sheets relating to Mrs. Lambert's first year at Helen Newberry dormitory, 1915-1916. Six sheets devoted to the summer activities, 1916-1917. Four sheets show the Library School class of 1917 its August picnic and the library bindery with William C. Holland.)
  - Scrapbook, of Lambert, née Novy, containing programs and mementoes of school activities while a student at the University of Michigan., 1910-1913 (Box 1)
- Genealogical and other research materials
  - Calendar of articles from the Detroit Gazette about the University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, and Washtenaw County, 1817-1830 (Box 1)
  - Death and marriage notices from Michigan newspapers at the Michigan Historical Collections, 14 volumes
    - Adrian, 1838-1865 (Volume 1)
    - Allegan County, Barry County, Bay County, Berrien County, Branch County (Volume 2)
    - Ann Arbor (death notices only), 1829-1867 (Volume 3)
    - Ann Arbor (marriage notices only), 1856-1866 (Volume 4)
    - Calhoun County (Volume 5)
    - Calhoun County (Volume 6)
      (continued)
    - Eaton County, Genesee County, Grand Traverse County (Volume 7)
    - Hillsdale County (Volume 8)
    - Hillsdale County, Houghton County, Ingham County (Volume 9)
    - Jackson County, Kalamazoo County, Kent County (Volume 10)
    - Lenawee County, Livingston County, Montcalm County, Oakland County, Ontonagon County, Ottawa County (Volume 11)
    - Wayne County (death notices) (Volume 12)
    - Wayne County (marriage notices) (Volume 13)
    - Saginaw County, St. Joseph County, Washtenaw County (Ypsilanti), Bay County (Bay City), Genesee County (Fenton), Jackson County (Jackson) (Volume 14)